

Meike Zehlike

PhD Researcher – Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Since April 2016 I am a Ph.D. researcher at the *Social & Information Systems* group of MPI-SWS Saarbrücken and Humboldt Universität zu Berlin, Germany. Before I worked as a software developer and scrum master in Berlin. I am a 2017 grantee of the Data Transparency Lab Research grant and a Google WTM scholar of 2019. My research interests center around artificial intelligence and its social impact, automatic discrimination discovery and algorithmic fairness, as well as the use of artificial intelligence in medical applications.

Education

2016 - present Ph.D. Researcher, Humboldt Universität zu Berlin, Berlin.

Research on Discrimination Discovery and Algorithmic Fairness.

Expecting to graduate by August 2020.

2010 – 2014 **Diploma Degree**, *Technische Universität Dresden*, Dresden, Germany.

graduated 02/2014 with grade 1.5

2010 **Semester abroad**, *INSA*, Lyon, France.

Computer Science

2009 –2010 Semester abroad, MIIT, Moscow, Russia.

Data Security

2006 – 2009 Basic Studies, Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, Germany.

Computer Science and Arts

Diploma Thesis (2014)

title Pattern Recognition of Vascular Pathologies at the Cortex in Thermographic Sequences

grade 1.4 - very good

Experience

2019 Visiting Researcher, VIDA Lab, New York University, New York City, USA.

Collaboration with Julia Stoyanovich

2019 – present Research Associate, Max Planck Institute for Software Systems, Saarbrücken.

Research Associate at Social and Information Systems group

2018 **Visiting Researcher**, group WSSC, Universidad Pompea Fabra, Barcelona, Spain.

Collaboration with Carlos Castillo

2016 – 2019 Research Associate, Technische Universität Berlin, Berlin.

Research associate and lecturer at CIT institute

2014 - 2016 Web Application Developer and Scrum Master, Projektron GmbH, Berlin.

Project manager and leader of a team of seven developers Web application development of project management software

2013 – 2014 Research Assistant, Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden.

Design and implementation of a model of the brain surface temperature

Design and implementation of a pattern recognition algorithm to find vascular pathologies

Analysis, visualization and presentation of the results

Projects

2018–2019 FairSearch, Project co-leader, Algorithm Research.

Implementation of stand-alone programming libraries for fair search results in Java and Python, plus an interface to Elasticsearch for both. Java and Python. https://github.com/fair-search

Awards and Scholarships

2019 Google Women Techmaker Scholarship EMEA.

Scholarship of 7000€ to support research and career. Attended Google student retreat in London.

2017 – 2019 Data Transparency Lab Research Grant.

Grant of 50,000€ for the design and implementation of web tools that enable fairness accountability and transparency in machine learning systems

2016 - 2019 SOAMED Graduate School.

PhD school on service-oriented Architectures for the Integration of Software-based Processes, exemplified by Health Care Systems and Medical Technology

2010 – 2012 Femtec Network, Career Building Scholarship.

Career building program for female future leaders from science, technology, engineering and mathematics

2010 Erasmus Scholarship.

Exchange abroad in Lyon, France

2009 DAAD "GoEast" Scholarship.

Semester abroad in Moscow, Russia

2009 DAAD Summer School Tomsk/Moscow Scholarship.

Language Summer School in preparation of the exchange in Moscow

Publications

Vocational

- 2019 Matching Code and Law: Achieving Algorithmic Fairness with Optimal Transport, Meike Zehlike, Philipp Hacker, Emil Wiedemann, Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery. 1/2020.
- 2019 FairSearch: A Tool for Fairness in Ranked Search Results, Meike Zehlike, Tom Sühr, Carlos Castillo, Ivan Kitanovski, Proceedings of the Web Conference 2020. WWW, 2020, Taipeh, Taiwan.
- 2019 Two-Sided Fairness for Repeated Matchings in Two-Sided Markets: A Case Study of a Ride-Hailing Platform, Tom Sühr, Asia J. Biega, Meike Zehlike, Krishna P. Gummadi and Abhijnan Chakraborty, Proceedings of the 2019 Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. SIGKDD, 2019.
- 2019 FairSearch: A Programming Library for Fair Search Results, Meike Zehlike, Carlos Castillo, Ivan Kitanovski, DSSGW@WWW 2019, San Francisco, US. Extended Abstract.
- 2018 Disparate Exposure in Learning to Rank, Meike Zehlike, European Symposium Series on Societal Challenges in Computational Social Science. 2018, Cologne, Germany. Poster Presentation
- 2018 Reducing Disparate Exposure in Ranking: A Learning To Rank Approach, *Meike Zehlike and Carlos Castillo*, Proceedings of the Web Conference 2020. WWW, 2020, Taipeh, Taiwan.
- 2017 Frameworks of Bias in Computer Systems and Their Application in Rankings, *Meike Zehlike*, DAB@CIKM 2017, Singapore.
- 2017 **FA*IR: A Fair Top-k Ranking Algorithm**, *Meike Zehlike, Francesco Bonchi, Carlos Castillo, Sara Hajian, Mohamed Megahed, and Ricardo Baeza-Yates*, Proceedings of the 2017 ACM on Conference on Information and Knowledge Management. ACM, 2017, Singapore.

Miscellaneous

- 2019 **Algorithmen gegen Diskriminierung**, *Meike Zehlike and Gert G. Wagner*, Gegenblende Debattenmagazin, 22. Mai 2019, https://gegenblende.dgb.de/artikel/++co++2b8f6854-7c67-11e9-9f8e-52540088cada.
- 2019 Unfair, Meike Zehlike and Gert G. Wagner, Süddeutsche Zeitung Nr. 104, 6. Mai 2019, Seite 9.

2016 Mit Scrum mehr Chancengleichheit in der Softwareentwicklung (*Improving Equality of Opportunity in Software Development with Scrum*), Meike Zehlike and Helena Barke., projektManagement aktuell volume(2/12).

Invited Talks And TV Appearances

- 03/2020 Fairness in Algorithmic Decision Making, FTA Live 2020, Berlin, Germany
- 02/2020 Panel Discussion: Wie wird künstliche Intelligenz geschlechtergerecht?, Technische Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany
- 12/2019 Matching Code and Law, Columbia University, New York City, NY, USA
- 12/2019 Matching Code and Law, IBM Research, Yorktown, NY, USA
- 11/2019 Disparate Exposure in Learning to Rank, Microsoft Research, New York City, NY, USA
- 10/2019 Fairness-Aware Ranking Algorithms, CapGemini, Germany
- 10/2019 Fairness in Algorithmic Decision Making, Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA
- 07/2019 **Fairness-Aware Ranking Algorithms**, *Technische Universität Berlin, ALGO Lab*, Berlin, Germany
- 06/2019 Panel Discussion on Data-Bias in Journalism, nr19 Jahreskonferenz, Hamburg, Germany
- 04/2019 **Fairness-Aware Ranking Algorithms**, Freie Universität Berlin, Human-centered Computing, Berlin, Germany
- 09/2018 Fairness-Aware Ranking Algorithms, RWTH Aachen, HumTec Group, Aachen, Germany
- 04/2018 Algorithms rule us all., VPRO Documentary, https://www.vpro.nl/programmas/tegenlicht/kijk/afleveringen/2017-2018/verslaafd-aan-het-algoritme.html, https://youtu.be/NFF_wj5jmiQ, Amsterdam, The Netherlands
- 11/2017 Frameworks of Bias in Computer Systems and Their Application in Rankings, *Workshop on Data and Algorithmic Bias, DAB 2017*, Singapore
- 11/2017 **Panel Discussion on Algorithmic Fairness**, *Workshop on Data an Algorithmic Bias, DAB 2017*, Singapore
- 03/2017 **On Fairness in Ranked Search Algorithms**, *Universität Hamburg, Language Technology Group*, Hamburg, Germany
- 12/2016 **IoT, Big Data and Machine Learning in the Context of Intelligent Sewage Systems**, *VDI Wissensforum*, Stuttgart, Germany

Professional Service

- 2020 PC member SIGIR 2020, PC Member BIAS 2020, Track Chair Informatik 2020.
- 2019 PC Member FACTS-IR 2019, Subreviewer EDBT 2019.
- 2017 2019 Academic Senate Member, Faculty Board Member, TU Berlin, Berlin, Germany.
 - 2018 Subreviewer for FAT*2019. PC Member SIGIR 2018.
- 2017 2018 **Appointment Committee Member**, *TU Berlin*, Berlin, Germany.

 Research associate deputy of the appointment committee for the Software and Business Engineering chair Research associate deputy of the appointment committee for the INGC chair

Teaching And Supervision

Lecturer

- 10/2018 03/2019 **Practical Project for Master Students**, *Institute for Complex Systems*, TU Berlin. Programming project to implement a website to explain bias and discrimination in computer systems
- 10/2017 03/2018 **Practical Course for Bachelor Students**, *Institute for Complex Systems*, TU Berlin. Programming project to implement the FA*IR algorithm as a plugin into Elasticsearch and Solr

Master Thesis Supervision

- Michal Jirku Algorithmic Fairness Development in a Competitive Setting
- Frederic Mauss Creating a gender-specific data set about the users of StackOverflow.
- Stefanie Quach Extending the DELTR Algorithm to Multinomial Use Cases

Bachelor Thesis Supervision

Flora Muscinelli

Tom Sühr

Two-Sided Fairness for Repeated Matchings in Two-Sided Markets

Jan Steffen Preßler

Gina Diehn

Simon Huber

Generating Discriminatory Datasets by Usage of Wasserstein Generative Adversarial Networks

Laura Mons

Hyerim Hwang

Languages

Mapping Algorithmic Fairness is Contextual

Two-Sided Markets

A Data Collection to Develop Fair Machine Learning Algorithms

FA*IR as Pre-Processing Fair Machine Learning Approach

Generative Adversarial Networks

Benchmarking for Fair Machine Learning Algorithms

Extension of the FA*IR Top-k Ranking Algorithm to Multinomial Use Cases

Languages

German (native), English (fluent), Russian (advanced), French (advanced), Finnish (basic)

Technologies

Programming Languages Python, Java, Matlab/Octave, C/C++